<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
	<channel>
		<title>Stephan Schwab</title>
		<description>As International Software Development Coach and Trainer I offer to CEOs and Department Leaders technical and organizational team coaching as a professional service to improve the value creation chain within their organization and to improve the quality of the product they are making.</description>		
		<link>http://0.0.0.0:4000</link>
		<atom:link
			href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />  <item>
			<title>Flowing Seasonal Creek</title>  <description>&lt;p&gt;After some 50 liters of #rain over the last two days I went out with the camera to document how the seasonal #creek looks like. The YouTube community around &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/@ProjectGranjaCaimito&quot;&gt;Project Granja Caimito&lt;/a&gt; had been making a lot of good suggestions on how to improve that creek for better #water #retention and today was a great opportunity to add some real world data to it and show how past modifications of the creek work with flowing water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the video I also talk about the catchment area on the neighbor’s land and further improvements that we want to make once we have a big excavator and dump truck here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/GV3G2mcd6ag?si=IWVwemVpxOrll77a&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2024/02/12/flowing-seasonal-creek.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/2024/02/12/flowing-seasonal-creek.html</guid>
				<hashtags>andalusia, homesteading, ecosystem, spain, drought</hashtags>
		</item>  <item>
			<title>Granja Caimito - The story so far</title>  <description>&lt;p&gt;Every large undertaking will inevitably pivot at some point. Rarely do ventures go as planned. This article is about reflecting where we started, what happened and what might be the new direction of the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the end of 2017 we purchased 45 hectares of Dehesa land in Andalusia, Spain. There have been a &lt;a href=&quot;/2017/10/02/new-farm-in-andalucia.html&quot;&gt;few blog posts about this new venture here on the blog&lt;/a&gt; but mostly the journey got documented on YouTube as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/@ProjectGranjaCaimito&quot;&gt;Project Granja Caimito&lt;/a&gt;. About 6500 subscribers, at the time of this writing, to the YouTube channel find it interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between then and now we’ve had a herd of up to 50 head of cattle, several times some 30 pigs and also flocks of 30 chicken and 9 sheep. We have eaten meat from our own animals and continue to have a freezer full of high-quality meat that’s not available in a regular supermarket. Today we have four horses and 8 big dogs around as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The land changed significantly and we have a lot more trees and other plants than before. And still the journey has just begun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;considerations&quot;&gt;Considerations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial thought was to buy raw land and develop it instead of buying a single-family home near a metropolitan center. When you buy a regular house with a garden you acquire basically a liability. That’s pretty much the same as when you buy a car. None of these things are really an asset because they require constant maintenance and therefore expenditures and do not produce anything. They do give you a benefit but the moment you stop their upkeep sooner (car) or later (house) you will lose the function the provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plus there is a ton of dependencies and in times of crisis (think about what happened to many people during the pandemic) these dependencies can become a real problem. Once you run out of income all the services that you’ve been taken for granted can and will get turned off. It’s not nice to sit in a fancy home in the dark and cold. Or the nice car that ran out of gas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also wanted to buy our piece of raw land in an area where there is nothing of interest around and likely very few other humans. So we looked at the map of Europe and eventually decided on the piece we bought in Spain because we happen to speak Spanish amongst other languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might ask “why with nothing of interest around?” and the answer is: safety. Not that I am overly pessimistic nor do I expect civil unrest or much worse a war but anywhere where a lot of people live in a small space the likelyhood of something unpleasant is a lot higher than somewhere out in the woods. At best one has to cross a river or a deep valley to get to your place or at least a 4x4 vehicle should be required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another related aspect is that in a rural place with few people around there is fewer rules about what you can and cannot do on your own land and so there is more freedom to enjoy. The other side of that coin is that you are responsible for everything and nobody will come and help. You need to &lt;em&gt;lift your own weight&lt;/em&gt; but that’s something I like in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Currently the people in the villages here in the Valle de los Pedroches face a serious problem with the public water services. What comes out of the faucet is bad water and people cannot drink it nor use it to bath if they have sensitive skin. The municipalities are trucking in water to help out but it’s a critical situation. We on our land have several shallow wells and do not face the issue at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;to-be-on-the-land&quot;&gt;To be on the land&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2018 was spent to built some basic infrastructure and a temporary house including a small solar system to have some electricity. And I can report that we all are very glad to have &lt;a href=&quot;/house/&quot;&gt;built a house&lt;/a&gt; instead of using our Mongolian yurt or an RV or camper van. We would have been miserable the whole time as the temperatures here can be extreme. In winter it is wet and can get down to -15º celsius while in summer it is very dry and can reach 42º celsius in the shade. Most of the time there is a temperature swing of 20º  between night and day. Our temporary house with air conditioning and all the amenities of the 21st century is serving us well up to today. We are about to build a real one now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;it-is-actually-about-restoring-a-damaged-ecosystem&quot;&gt;It is actually about restoring a damaged ecosystem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we were trying out different things with plants and animals we learned that our piece of land as well as the vast landscape all around it is actually pretty damaged. Damaged from decades or more of abuse and extractive practices where the benefit for the human exploiting the land was more important than being a good steward of the land. There are many reasons for that and the space here and now isn’t big enough to go further into this. However, I do understand why things are the way they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To us that meant we could not simply start with some sort of production to offer a product. We first have to restore the land in order to eventually be able to sell the surplus once it emerges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;can-we-derive-a-long-term-income-from-it&quot;&gt;Can we derive a long-term income from it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We thought about potential income or at least food from the land before we purchased it. However we didn’t really know how agriculture or ranching actually works. Or how to approach customers. It’s not like as you could roll up to a supermarket and sell them your fresh produce or meat on the spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see by looking around on this website, our income does not depend on agriculture and so we can afford to learn from our mistakes and failures and over time we should be able to derive an income from the land and it’s very likely going to be some niche product/service and certainly not from a commodity. There have been some successful experiments with direct sales of ham and hot chilis in the shop over at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.caimito.eu/shop&quot;&gt;caimito.eu&lt;/a&gt;. I am especially happy about the pricing slider where the customer picks their own price based on the value of the product as they perceive it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;failures&quot;&gt;Failures&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between early 2019 and 2023 we all learned a good deal about things that were unknown to us in the beginning and we did have a few severe failures. Everything around animals and plants or systems wasn’t really an issue but instead we had people problems. Problems with people we hired. I don’t intent to disclosure details here although I did mention a few things in the YouTube videos. The issues mostly revolve around motivation of the people you hire and not everybody likes to be part of a team but instead prefers to draw a salary and work as being told instead of contributing to a venture with their own creativity. That’s perfectly fine for a factory worker or similar but it does kill a venture easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A project such as ours was supposed to offer an opportunity for learning, personal growth and building up something for the benefit of the whole group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we stopped that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of trying to build a &lt;em&gt;team&lt;/em&gt; we have now switched to the concept of &lt;em&gt;crew&lt;/em&gt; which means we hire experienced people for something like a specific &lt;em&gt;journey&lt;/em&gt; (as on a cruise ship or airplane) and there is no long-term commitment or learning required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;new-phase&quot;&gt;New phase&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now in 2024 we have entered a new phase for our project. It continues to be an effort to restore the ecosystem on our land but we have put our focus on things that matter to us personally while still putting things in motion for some long-term income without jeopardizing the ecosystem restoration effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the story so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested, follow along here and also on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/@ProjectGranjaCaimito&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt; to watch what we do in our videos that are made and published frequently.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2024 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2024/02/11/granja-caimito.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/2024/02/11/granja-caimito.html</guid>
				<hashtags>farming, andalusia, venture, livestock, homesteading, ecosystem, dehesa, spain, offgrid</hashtags>
		</item>  <item>
			<title>Automated posting from blog to social networks</title>  <description>&lt;p&gt;Now that the landscape of social networks has widened I’ve thought a bit about how I can keep my content on my website and still reach people on the different networks. The result is a small JavaScript program that allows me to publish content from my blog, which was established in 2006, to X/Twitter, Mastodon and soon other networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My blog exposes an RSS feed. RSS is a way to syndicate content from different sources and is based on XML. The social networks all have an API that allows automated posting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I signed up for the developer program at X/Twitter and registered an application there in order to obtain access credentials. I did the same at the Mastodon instance I have an account at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My little program now loops through the items in my own RSS feed and creates a post for each network. It has to shorten the text to the character limit each network imposes and it also adds some hashtags if present in my blog article. Then it adds a link to the full article and posts it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I had to make a choice that I never liked. I started to use the most promising social network to participate and stopped writing blog articles. There is more reach and more interaction on a social network with millions of users than one could ever achieve on a humble blog that only a few people know about. The downside is that now one’s own content is now being given away to the social network and who knows what will happen to it over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some social networks would like to convince people to create on their platform and so they offer a financial incentive and pay creators for their time and content. That’s probably why Twitter - now X - increased the character limit so that people can publish actual full-length articles on their platform. I am not after the money but instead my motivation is to share and reap a non-monetary benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With my new script I can now write an article like this one, keep it on my own platform - my blog - and notify all my followers on all the social networks I like to participate in. If I use hashtags I might even reach more people beyond my followers. They get to see a teaser of the article and if interested they will click through to this website where they can read the whole article and maybe also discover more content of my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are commercial services to achieve a similar thing and I have used some of them before. But nothing beats the comfort and ease of use I have now. I just write my article, do a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;git push&lt;/code&gt; and I’m done. It’s all automated and leaves me more time for other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously I want and need to participate in the social networks I post to. That way I can answer to replies or comments and also see what’s being talked about. It’s not a one-way street.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Sat, 10 Feb 2024 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2024/02/10/article.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/2024/02/10/article.html</guid>
				<hashtags>social, networks, blogging, software_development</hashtags>
		</item>  <item>
			<title>Concrete Work, Solar System, Rain in the Forecast - And an Announcement</title>  <description>&lt;p&gt;Another video about our project at Granja Caimito. This time we did some concrete work and enjoy the benefits of our enlarged solar system for more power for free - after the installation that is. We are also expecting some good rain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watch it on YouTube: https://youtu.be/8aQxOJHqRUE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8aQxOJHqRUE?si=IvziDLau8dcEhPUU&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

</description>
				
				<pubDate>Fri, 09 Feb 2024 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2024/02/09/concrete-work-solar-system-rain.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/2024/02/09/concrete-work-solar-system-rain.html</guid>
				<hashtags>spain, homesteading, solarpower, concrete</hashtags>
		</item>  <item>
			<title>An update about Living on the farm</title>  <description>&lt;p&gt;Well… It has been a long while since I posted something here. Some might even think
that something has happened or that I’ve lost interested in the topics I’ve written about before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything is just fine and a lot of positive things have happened. Quite a lot. Actually that much that there wasn’t any time or power left to start writing here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been doing a lot of videos instead of writing articles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/wFATFYh7L3k&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The site &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;granja.caimito.net&lt;/code&gt; does not exist anymore. Instead there will be a new one in a while.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2022/05/02/update.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/2022/05/02/update.html</guid>
				<hashtags></hashtags>
		</item>  <item>
			<title>Living on the farm</title>  <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s been a while since I wrote anything here on this website. The last post was about &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/12/29/spent-the-night-in-the-new-house.html&quot;&gt;trying out the new house&lt;/a&gt; we built ourselves. Since then six months have past. Wow! A long time and I have to say that time went by in a hurry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have been pretty busy with all kinds of work at the farm and elsewhere. I was also working as a Consultant for a new client in Belgrade, Serbia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a new website for all things related to the farm. It’s address is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://granja.caimito.net&quot;&gt;http://granja.caimito.net&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is how it looks like. The opening picture was taken sometime in March 2019. On that website I’ve written a lot about what we’ve been doing on the farm so far. Most content is in English while other languages lack behind. It’s tough to find the time to write and even tougher to write the same thing again in other languages. I hope we can fix that soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/2019-07-09-living-on-the-farm/granja-caimito.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since a couple of days I also have a real horse again. The horse is a mare and her name is Sacagewea. The name refers to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sacagawea&quot;&gt;Shoshone Indian woman&lt;/a&gt; who helped the Lewis and Clark expedition. She was raised and educated by &lt;a href=&quot;http://caballosnaturalmente.com/&quot;&gt;Carlos Ponferrada&lt;/a&gt; who wanted to scale down a bit and offered some horses to other people. I was lucky to receive Sacagewea and her friend Tuscarora, another mare he named after this &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tuscarora_people&quot;&gt;tribe&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/2019-07-09-living-on-the-farm/2019-06-30_15-31-55.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These horses are very people-focused. Whenever you come near them they come to you and look for a hug and some grooming, which is horse’s smalltalk. Riding them requires minimal input and everything goes by the legs or seat. The reins are almost innecessary. They do have personality and here and there tell the other “leave me alone”. So far I used Sacagewea to get around the farm, we moved cows a little bit. We did nothing too exciting and definetely did not chase any cows. There is too many stones around. It might be dangerous to gallop behind a cow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://granja.caimito.net&quot;&gt;http://granja.caimito.net&lt;/a&gt; for more farm related articles.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2019 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2019/07/09/living-on-the-farm.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/2019/07/09/living-on-the-farm.html</guid>
				<hashtags></hashtags>
		</item>  <item>
			<title>Spent the night in the new house</title>  <description>&lt;p&gt;The new house is - as every major project is - 95% done. All the major functionality is there, most of it is working and intented but there is a myriad of tiny little things that isn’t quite right or even needs to be redone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So… Let’s get started and close the gate:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/2018-12-29-spent-the-night-in-the-new-house/IMG_2584.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then get organized a little bit. There are still quite a few leftovers from construction and many appliances are installed temporarily. There is also furniture missing and the whole place is a mess. However, that doesn’t matter for this test. Neither do the missing door trims or the doors themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/2018-12-29-spent-the-night-in-the-new-house/IMG_2586.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next morning was quite chilly. I don’t have anything to tell me the outside temperature but the information from a weather station nearby. It said 0C. As you can see in the picture that sounds about right:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/2018-12-29-spent-the-night-in-the-new-house/IMG_2592.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A look out the other bedroom window showed these guys having breakfast at dawn:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/2018-12-29-spent-the-night-in-the-new-house/IMG_2595.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How did the test go you might ask. Well let’s see:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I had a power failure early on because the whole day was foggy and the batteries were not charged. Using the gas powered generator solved that but the generator has a smaller power rating than the inverter of the solar system, which then led to the first outage due to overload.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I had two electrical failures due to overload. The 3000W inverter is not enough. The water heater puts the system beyond the limit when it turns on while other consumers are drawing power. The water heater has a 100 liters tank that it keeps hot. It is efficient from a yearly consumption perspective but creates a problem in our setting as it can turn on at any moment and create an overload.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When the power is out the pellet stove stops working as it needs current for its fans and to load pellets. A pellet stove is a nice idea to offset the high cost of utility power sold to you but if you make your own power the cost is fix and your worry is power generation and storage and not the monthly charge from the utility company.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Water pressure is great, but it turns out we have a few leaks at some fittings.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Turning off the pellet stove at bedtime gets you up at 5 AM to turn it back on. Every structure looses heat and the heat loss has to be compensated by some heat source. I think the house looses about 1 degree Celcius in 10 hours.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then this view from the kitchen window made up for the “hardship”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/2018-12-29-spent-the-night-in-the-new-house/IMG_2601.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the sun rose the solar system started to charge and these guys are making sure to warm up as well:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/2018-12-29-spent-the-night-in-the-new-house/horse-sheep.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I have a list of things to fix or to improve and hopefully we will get to 100% done soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Sat, 29 Dec 2018 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2018/12/29/spent-the-night-in-the-new-house.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/2018/12/29/spent-the-night-in-the-new-house.html</guid>
				<hashtags></hashtags>
		</item>  <item>
			<title>Working on the inside of the house</title>  <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s been a whole month since I posted about our house build. Lots of things have been going on. Not only are we working on the house itself but we have to take care of the animals as well. Most of them feed themselves as we are now in the rainy part of the year and the pasture grows nicely. The only ones we need to feed daily are the three pigs we have in a corral where they are working on producing plant feed. I will talk more about that in a separate post. The cows require a different kind of daily attention. We rotate them every second day onto a new paddock and for that we need to move electric fencing. That takes about an hour every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;drywall&quot;&gt;Drywall&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inside the house we have put up a lot of drywall with insulation behind. Installing the drywall sheets goes relatively quick but putting in all those screws takes time. Unfortunately to late for us but I did learn about a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Makita-XRF02Z-Lithium-Ion-Cordless-Screwdriver/dp/B010Q7FNZI&quot;&gt;better tool for the job&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What really takes up time is applying the drywall mud and cleaning up the surface. We had to learn to do it right by delivering a bad job first and then fixing it. Every wall is done better than the one before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the picture you can also see our new wood stove. It uses wood pellets and should keep us warm during fall and winter. As of the moment temperatures have dropped to something like 2C at night and 10C during the day. However, once the sun comes out here in Andalucia it gets very warm. Just make sure to stay in the sunlight. In the shade it is cold. A good idea is to put on a T-shirt in order to not sweat and then a vest over it to keep the upper body warm and protected from the wind. Don’t forget to protect the neck and throat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/2018-11-03-working-on-the-inside-of-the-house/IMG_1260.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;porches&quot;&gt;Porches&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally we also got around to make some of the porches in the front and back of the house. The material for that was lying around for months and had been partially used up for other things since then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the beginning of the front porch with some makeshift stair. In the background you can see that we still use some of the space to store drywall sheets to keep them dry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/2018-11-03-working-on-the-inside-of-the-house/IMG_1261.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the back we had a platform that came out of an earlier stage of the build when we were still trying to &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/06/23/adding-the-mongolian-yurt-to-the-building.html&quot;&gt;keep the house much simpler&lt;/a&gt;. The remaining portion is now closed up but still not completely finished. But at least we can now use the area and won’t fall into an open hole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/2018-11-03-working-on-the-inside-of-the-house/IMG_1094.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;floor&quot;&gt;Floor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two rooms have been fully painted, which allowed us to put in the insulated floor. We have XPS panels glued to the black plywood and on top of that wood flooring made by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.finsa.com/cs/Satellite?idiomaNav=en_US&amp;amp;c=CP_CatDiseno_P&amp;amp;pagename=FN_CatalogoProductos/CP_CatDiseno_P/CP_PTPortadaCatDiseno&amp;amp;cid=1426681569233&quot;&gt;Spanish company FINSA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This room is eventually going to be the office. At the moment we use it to prepare lunch while we are there during the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/2018-11-03-working-on-the-inside-of-the-house/IMG_1310.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next to it is the bedroom. It’s great to have a clean space again where we can put the furniture that we had to move into the construction site in August when we had to leave our temporary apartment and move into a much smaller one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/2018-11-03-working-on-the-inside-of-the-house/IMG_1311.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lights&quot;&gt;Lights&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We decided to have lots of LED panels in the ceiling. Maybe a bit too many but then it provides a lot of light. It’s like having the sun inside the room. Here is an impression of the still unfinished main area of the house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That much light feels good on the eyes. As most of the days here in Andalucia have bright sun outside it makes sense to have a similar amount of light inside the house. That avoids the shock when going outside and when going inside you don’t step into a dark room and need to wait a moment to adapt. Our electric energy is free as the sun provides it via the solar panels. The LED panels don’t consume much and don’t get warm at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/2018-11-03-working-on-the-inside-of-the-house/IMG_0987.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;heating&quot;&gt;Heating&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I prepare this blog post we are finishing up on installing these tiles that will support the weight of the wood stove and provide a surface that won’t suffer when ash finds its way onto it while cleaning the stove.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/2018-11-03-working-on-the-inside-of-the-house/IMG_1331.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;drowing-in-new-growth&quot;&gt;Drowing in new growth&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now during fall we are getting quite a bit of rain every few days followed by days with a lot of sunshine. That makes the plants grow and we are starting to get drowned by vegetation around the house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/2018-11-03-working-on-the-inside-of-the-house/IMG_1288.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sheep are enjoying it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;393&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/e9TnVQwtn-M?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Sat, 03 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2018/11/03/working-on-the-inside-of-the-house.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/2018/11/03/working-on-the-inside-of-the-house.html</guid>
				<hashtags></hashtags>
		</item>  <item>
			<title>Solar pump for the shallow well</title>  <description>&lt;p&gt;A few weeks back we decided to improve our water supply. Before we had been using a gasoline powered pump to fill the water tank from the well once in a while. The problem with that is that it makes noise, the tank empties out and water pressure drops and then one has to act before running out of water. And these pumps tend to break or one runs out of gasoline. That’s not a good thing. There is a better way available and it’s free after the initial investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we ordered the installation of a solar powered pump. We are all busy with finishing the house thus it made sense to simply use some money instead of buying the pieces and figuring it out ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/2018-10-04-solar-pump-for-the-shallow-well/solarpump-1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all did have a good luck at what the professionals were doing to learn how it’s being done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pump is a longish cylinder that gets sunk into the well and hangs there at a depth of about 7 meters. The 40 mm pipe and the power cable is attached to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/2018-10-04-solar-pump-for-the-shallow-well/solarpump-2.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the post with the solar panels on top we’ve got some switches. We can turn on the pump manually and we can switch the power source to a generator in case there is not enough sunlight or we need to pump at night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/2018-10-04-solar-pump-for-the-shallow-well/solarpump-3.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: 0; margin-right: 15px; margin-top: 0&quot; src=&quot;/img/posts/2018-10-04-solar-pump-for-the-shallow-well/solarpump-4.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of the water tower the professionals installed a buoy that closes a valve. When it’s shut, pressure will build up in the pipe and a pressure switch close to the pump will trigger a power shutoff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img align=&quot;right&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: 15px; margin-right: 0; margin-top: 0&quot; src=&quot;/img/posts/2018-10-04-solar-pump-for-the-shallow-well/solarpump-5.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design of our water distribution system is currently entirely driven by dynamic demand. We are not yet living in the house but we have a number of animals that have a need for water. That triggered the installation of a new water pipe of 32 mm in diameter. We did take into account future needs and the pipe takes a bit of a detour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good thing is that we don’t need to rely anymore on portable IBC water tanks. As the sunlight creates a lot of algae growth, connecting the waterers for the animals directly to a pipe gets also rid of that problem. One thing less to worry about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will certainly be a lot of redesigns as we learn what we really need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br clear=&quot;all&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Thu, 04 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2018/10/04/solar-pump-for-the-shallow-well.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/2018/10/04/solar-pump-for-the-shallow-well.html</guid>
				<hashtags></hashtags>
		</item>  <item>
			<title>Air conditioner for the offgrid house</title>  <description>&lt;p&gt;This week we added two air conditioners to the house. They are split units. One for the bedroom and the other for the office. The &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/07/19/solar-power-for-the-house.html&quot;&gt;solar system&lt;/a&gt; has been working fine and recently we were using it for &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/08/04/washing-and-drying-with-solar-power.html&quot;&gt;washing and drying other clothes&lt;/a&gt; with pure solar power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inside unit is mounted at the high point of the ceiling and the fan moves the cold air in such a way that it does not hit people directly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/2018-08-31-air-conditioner-for-the-offgrid-house/ac-1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outdoor unit is mounted on two wooden brackets that are nailed to the subfloor of the house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/2018-08-31-air-conditioner-for-the-offgrid-house/ac-2.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we put on the siding this will be covered and framed nicely. As it is right now it is fully functional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/2018-08-31-air-conditioner-for-the-offgrid-house/ac-3.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running one unit consumes a maximum of 1200 W as shown on the inverter. That includes the loss inside of the inverter. We had an outside temperature of about 35 degrees Celcius and the A/C cooled down the house to less than 25 degrees Celcius in a short amount of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our current solar system only provides us 1980 W from the panels and we cannot connect more than 6 330 W panels. That means we have to be smart about what to turn on and when. We are getting two more batteries to have a total storage capacity of 500 Ah. We do have plans to have a much bigger system so that power becomes a non-issue. What we did learn so far is how solar works, what it can do for us in our offgrid situation and what the cost of it is. So far there is nothing to complain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… and it is pretty cool to be able to work inside :-)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Fri, 31 Aug 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2018/08/31/air-conditioner-for-the-offgrid-house.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/2018/08/31/air-conditioner-for-the-offgrid-house.html</guid>
				<hashtags></hashtags>
		</item>  </channel>
</rss>